foreign
[Music]
hello everyone good day good evening
wherever you are welcome to the 58th
live episode of the ask abhijit show
so as you know today is an interactive
episode i'm going to be taking your
questions from the live chat so let's
see who all we have today
who all is there with us right now
[Applause]
good evening good day wherever you are
very nice to see you all thank you so
much for being here
so today like i said is going to be an
interactive session i'm going to take
all your all your questions from the
live chat right now so let's see what
questions you have asked thus far
uh let us take a look at the questions
that are there thus far um let's see
what do we have
okay this is an interesting question by
khusro anushiravan
what
what is your view on me and justinian of
a relationship with india
so i'm assuming that you mean these the
persian sassanian king
khusro anushiravan i think he
he ruled persia i think in the sixth
century a.d
in the middle of the 6th century 80 i
think he his reign was quite long he
ruled for 40 50 years i think if i'm not
mistaken there something like that
approximately
and he is considered to be one of the
greatest uh kings of persia of iran
and he did enter into significant
conflicts with the byzantine empire
which is the eastern roman empire whose
capital was byzantium or constantinople
present-day istanbul in turkey
so uh and i think that the conflict
which she had with the
uh byzantine empire lasted for quite a
while it was an ongoing conflict most
likely it uh
the conflict went on beyond khosrow's
deaths
so yeah that's what i can remember right
now um
he is considered to be one of the
greatest things he was considered to be
a philosopher king he was a big patron
of the arts and the literature and
literature and all that philosophy etc
and if i'm not mistaken he also did
enter into a conflict with the
hephthalite
empire
which is the
shweta huna's the white hans who did
rule
certain parts of northern india at that
time
in the
sixth century a.d
so he did enter into a conflict with the
haptilites and i think he was able to
defeat them
to a certain extent in an alliance with
another turkic confederation i think it
was the gok turks
so that's what i recall right now off
the top of my head about uh khusro
justinian was the emperor of the byzant
was the byzantine empire emperor at the
time
and yeah these two did enter into a
significant conflict they had they had a
ceasefire then the ceasefire was broken
again either either by kosovo or by
justinian i don't remember right now but
yeah it's a very interesting chapter of
history and khosrau is one of the most
significant kings
of persia
in the
first and second millennium a.d
i think he was so great that later
kings of persia took on the title of
khusro
just to
bask in some of the reflected glory
and what relationship did he have with
india i'm not sure about his
relationship with india did he have any
significant
relationship with india
at the time certain parts of northern
india were ruled by the
were under attack or were ruled by the
hephthalites the shwetahunas the white
hans
and i think this was the period of the
gupta empire in india
more or less approximately
and i'm not sure what sort of
relationship was there between the
between the sasanian persians and the
gupta empire of india
but it's something that uh yeah i think
i can look up and maybe speak about if i
find something interesting as far as as
i recall khosrow's major camp campaigns
were to the west of persia with the
ottoman empire he conquered parts of the
uh sorry the the
byzantine empire and he conquered parts
of territories that belong to the
byzantines
he i think he
was able to go and bathe in the
mediterranean sea because of his
conquests and so on so he's a very
interesting figure
interesting figure in history and
certainly something that
people can
study if it interests them
so interesting question to start off
with
tanushri asks can you tell us about the
government of the harappan civilization
so you see the harappan
it was not a separate civilization it
was one phase one era of india's
civilization
so what was the government like is the
question well
what do we know about the harappan phase
of our civilization we know whatever we
know
from the archaeological
record
so we haven't been able to decipher the
script yet
and that is the reason why we don't know
much about the this phase of our
civilization we don't know what these
cities and towns were called we call
them harappa mohenjo-daro etc but these
are names we have given to these cities
today
we don't know what these cities were
called 5000 years ago so we have loved
lost that information
uh
so we haven't been able to decipher the
script thus far because most like mostly
because nobody has really taken
a significant interest and done it
seriously but what do we know about the
government we don't know anything about
the government
because we don't have any uh records
from the time we haven't been able to
decipher the script but from the
archaeological record what we find is
that there were no royal palaces
there were no royal palaces there the
largest and most prominent buildings
were public buildings
like um
like the meeting hall the town hall
the city hall the great bath
the store houses of grains and all
so this tells us that there was no
monarchy there
it was kind of a democratic government
that's what it looks like because in a
democracy the major buildings the most
prominent buildings are the buildings
that are in service to of the people
today in india the great grand buildings
of the government are the parliament
building and things like that
right we don't have royal palaces and so
on i mean that's what we find throughout
india's history we hardly ever find any
royal palace or any anything like that
so in the harappan phase of our
civilization we did not have any royal
palaces the greatest buildings were the
public buildings so it looks like there
was a form of democracy that was
prevalent at the time
so that's what we can say and there is a
total absence of warfare you don't find
any evidence of battles or warfare or
arms
or any such thing it was it is very
clear that this was a very peaceful
phase of our history
and it clearly looks like there was some
form of democracy
that was the form of governance so
that's what we can tell from the
information and the data that we have
at hand
thus far
okay let's take some of the questions
whose wisdom was more powerful
so that's an interesting question see
when you come when it comes to vishnu
gupta his wisdom is available in that
great book the arthashastra which is all
about how to govern a very large kingdom
or empire so it deals with everything it
deals with
taxation it deals with governance it
deals with the administration it deals
with the duties duties of the kings of
the king the duties of the various
officials it deals with statecraft with
spycraft with tradecraft it deals with
geopolitics it deals with warfare
conflict
it deals with how to spy
on your enemies even on your own people
in order to maintain law and order and
in order to find out
the those who are anti-nationals etc and
so on it is an encyclopedia
of governance and statecraft and
geopolitics and all that when it comes
to sun tzu
his treatise is called the art of war
it is simply
a set of stratagems it's not even a set
of strategies
it's a set of strategems which are
certain aphorisms or or
pieces of of nuggets of wisdom that can
be applied
in essentially in warfare but then they
can also be applied in business and in
various activities that involve
competition
between various parties
so sun tzu's
work is more
it is more focused on warfare
which also has significant applications
in business
etc
but chanakya's work is encyclopedic it
is far more than simply how to
uh
engage in warfare
so i would say that vishnu gupta
chanaki's work is far greater it has it
has a far greater scope
than the limited scope which is the
uh game theory conflict and all that of
sun tzu's work so these have different
applications and different contexts but
vishnu gupta chanaki's work is timeless
it is far larger in scope than the work
of sun tzu we don't even know if sanju
was a real person but let's just assume
that he was
so that in short is the answer
okay rahul paul says can ispa change
india's space program i can't remember
what is the full form of isp let me just
quickly
take a look what's isp indian society
indian space
association is it
indian space association so i think it
is a consortium of various companies
private companies etc
uh that are involved or are getting
involved in space so i think it's a very
good thing
and uh
it's good if private companies and
private operators were to join the space
program get involved in it the more the
merrier
we need to create an entire ecosystem
technological ecosystem that uh feeds
and supports the space program we can't
keep relying on just one organization
isro to do everything i mean look at the
way things are evolving the us today
earlier i mean just 20 years ago you you
only had one major operator which was
nasa and
today you have blue origin you have
space x of course
and you have the united launch alliance
which is another private operator it's a
consortium
and so on so nasa doesn't have to do
everything on their own they can
outsource work to these other companies
they can even uh
i mean give contracts to spacex etc to
launch cargo supplies and even
astronauts into space and so on and so
forth so it's always good if you have
multiple players in the scene in your
country
so i think it can certainly if it is
nurtured properly and it is if the
regulation and all if it is all sorted
out then it can certainly give a very
big boost in philip to the indian space
program which we certainly need because
i don't see
i mean isro is
isro is controlled by the government and
that is i think the primary reason why
we don't see too much innovation
happening in israel israel is a bunch of
brilliant scientists no doubt about it
they are very capable but
do you do we see them developing new
rockets more powerful rockets no we keep
on launching the same couple of rockets
for the past 10 years the pslv and
various iterations of the gslv very slow
iterative
improvements are being done to the gslv
the last test did not work out very well
unfortunately i hope the next one works
fine
but we are not seeing quantum leaps in
our capabilities the gslv is what's the
capability i think it's about 5000 kilos
5 tons or so to low earth orbit that's
the kind of payload approximately that
it can uh
take to low earth orbit
i think we need to significantly boost
these capabilities we need to build more
powerful rockets i mean today if you
want to send a spacecraft to the moon
you can't even do it in one shot you
need to keep uh
you know put the
spacecraft in earth's orbit and then
keep raising the orbit time of one step
at a time it takes two or three months
to reach the moon
but if the if you have a more powerful
rocket you can reach the moon in 20 48
to 72 hours just a straight shot so we
don't have
rockets with that kind of power as of
today so why is it not being done do we
not have the capability of course we
have the capability to do that
but you need government approval to do
this
and that's not happening why are we not
developing
uh reusable rockets
why aren't we developing the rockets
that the rocket boosters that can
land autonomously on their own and can
be reused why not
will that not cut down the cost of space
launches significantly that's what
spacex has done
so why isn't that being done it's not
because the scientists aren't capable of
doing that it's because the government
is not allowing to do them maybe it's a
lack of budget or lack of approvals i
don't i don't know what it is
so it is
very
important that private players get
involved in the space program
and when you have a private player with
then you see a lot of innovation
happening so if especially if you have a
lot of competition so i think the isp is
a good step
but it still remains to be seen in what
direction it goes but it is very
important that india
develops and
enhances augments its
space capabilities significantly in the
next
decade or two
because the future is space the
countries the two or three countries
nations that will lead the world
in space exploration in the 21st century
are the two or three countries that will
control
and and drive the direction of the world
that's how it is that's how it's going
to be so that's why india needs to wake
up and
and take its space capabilities to the
next level quickly
right okay let's take a look uh many of
the questions i can see have been
answered before let's take something
different
what is my view of a certain book well i
haven't read the book so
and some questions are being repeated
okay this is a question by harshit saini
will a third wave of corona come
i think only the media can create a
third wave of the corona
of the corona virus
you know which organizations those are
which would like to say the government
do very badly and fail
i'm not gonna take names but yeah
certain sections of the indian media are
always overjoyed when something bad
happens to india and they are the ones
who will try and create a new wave of
corona thus far
we have more than one billion
vaccinations done in india and it's
still going on very strongly
so i don't see why there should be a
third wave of corona when within a few
months
i think a significant
percentage of the indian population will
be fully vaccinated
and therefore they will be immune to the
virus and once you reach a certain
threshold of the population which is
immune to the virus there is no chance
of a new wave of the pandemic happening
so if it happens it will be a media
creation they will try and cherry pick
certain data points and try it and
present that to the public
as
a new wave or something i do not see any
such thing happening india has surpassed
all expectations in the way the pandemic
has been handled in the way
the
governance government infrastructure has
been used to vaccinate people
very
efficiently very rapidly it's incredible
how it's how it's happened the the
foreign media the american media a few
months ago was was going overboard and
predicting that millions of indians will
die of the coronavirus pandemic because
india's ability to vaccinate people is
very very poor et cetera well today
they're all quiet and they're hiding in
some corners somewhere so i don't see
any such thing happening i think we are
past the coronavirus pandemic very soon
we're gonna be past it very soon and we
need to look forward and move on as a
nation and build build build build
all right
okay love panda says as elon musk said
to make mars as hot as her the earth
we have to nuke mars is it possible to
nuke mars will it give the same result
as it gives on earth my views i have
answered this question a couple of times
but it's a fun question
so let's stick it up see elon musk is
not crazy
he did say that we should nuke mars and
all that's called humor
it's humor
nobody in their right mind would
actually go in nuke mars if you actually
want to send people there you don't want
all that radiation flying around in the
atmosphere
right
and a nuclear blast is something that
you can't really control i mean you can
control the um the yield the output and
all that depending on the weapon that
you have but that is not the right way
to do things it's going to create a
whole chain of
downstream effects that cannot be
foreseen or controlled so that is not
the way to nuke mars and even if you
nuke the north and south pole of mars
wherever you have all these ice caps and
all
it's not going to raise the temperature
all the way to the the kind of
temperatures we have on earth
it's going to melt some of the water
some of it
and it's not really going to be so
effective so terraforming mars
if it ever happens in the future is
going to be a project that will last
several centuries it won't happen in a
year or two or in a decade or two
and i don't know if we will ever be able
to reach the stage where we can do that
because it will take the kind of
technological capabilities industrial
capabilities that we don't have today
so new king mars is
humor
he nobody is serious when they talk
about nuking mars
i mean nobody in the right mind
would be seriously considering
detonating nuclear bombs
on mars i mean that's not the way to do
it do this
is it possible to nuke mars yeah yeah if
somebody is crazy enough and they they
can reach mars they can do it sure but
it will not give the results you want
because see
the most powerful nuclear weapon ever
tested was the tsar bomba i think it had
a
yield of 50 megatons of tnt
50 megatons i think it was yeah
and
so even if you use that to nuke the
the poles of mars i don't know whether
it will be able to actually melt all the
ice that is there
because the
heat dissipates very quickly in the
atmosphere you know
so i don't think it's really
uh something that's even worth doing
terraforming is a different it's a
long-term strategy and maybe concentric
mirrors in orbit around mars or
something like that needs to be
considered once we have the capabilities
so those are my views about new king
mars
okay let's take some more questions
this is an interesting question by sahil
we are reaching 8 billion people what's
the maximum population
earth can hold
i think we are already past the maximum
population that we can sustainably hold
on the planet because
you know a hundred years ago
more than 90 percent of the biomass
on the planet was wild animals
today more than 90 percent of the
biomass on the planet animal biomass
is
domestic animals
cattle livestock etc for human
consumption
so we have already wiped out most of the
wild animals that you have on the planet
we are causing so much deforestation
just to keep just to keep on sustaining
the human population on the planet
and the western nations they are so fond
of eating meat
and animal agriculture is the biggest
cause of pollution and deforestation on
the planet
people are deforesting the amazon
jungle to plant soybean plantations to
feed those cattle the cows that the
americans and other countries
slaughter millions of cows and other
animals every year
millions of billions of that i'm not
sure
so this is
extremely
harmful to the environment
and this is not sustainable i think
eight billion is is really we are
reaching the breaking point we may even
reach 10 billion in a few in a couple of
decades or so if the population growth
rate goes on the way it is going on
right now
so it is a very big problem we need to
find ways of slowing down the population
growth
and
we need to especially the western
nations the first so-called first world
nations they need to stop consuming so
much meat
so these are the challenges challenges
we're facing i don't know what is the
maximum population earth can the earth
can hold
i'm sure it can go on for some time but
then you will reach a phase when
something is going to go wrong and
you know
things will go really badly wrong and
you will see massive depopulation events
of some kind i mean nature will fight
back at some point in time
so i think we are going
in the wrong direction something needs
to be done urgently in the next two
three decades
and of course you cannot cut down or
cull the population we are human beings
everybody has human rights and all
but what we can do is to cut down the
growth rate of populations
so something like a two-child policy or
something
something like that needs to be enforced
maybe worldwide for a few decades
you know something like that so
people need to the leaders need to come
up with a viable solutions that don't
violate basic human rights in any way or
form
but certainly this is a huge challenge
so something needs to be done for sure
what do i think about the tamil language
i think it's a wonderful language
right let's take some more questions
vedanta asks why is there very less
information available about the kings
and dynasties of the mahajanapada time
period about their administrative style
social structure economic structure etc
we had all the information in the
written form in all our great
universities india a thousand years ago
india was a land of universities
you had dozens of great universities
like nalanda sheila vikram shilov
tilhara udantapuri and so on and so
forth all across the length and the
breadth of the country and then the
turkic invasions happened and all these
universities were destroyed and all the
libraries were burned
and that is why all our historical
records were destroyed and that is why
there is so little information
about all these kings and dynasties of
the mahajanapadas of the vedic age we
don't even know the names of the great
cities of the sapta sindhu region today
they call them harappa and mohenjo-daro
and kalibangan
etc these are modern names of these
places we don't know what they were
called 5000 years ago so we have lost
all of this information the
administration the social structure
economic structure the names of the
kings and dinosaurs etc and some records
still exist for example you have the
raja tarangiri of kalhana in which you
have these
very old
records of lineages of dynastic lineages
etc but historians say that this is all
mythology it's all made up and it is not
quite historically accurate and so on
and so forth we do still have many of
these old lineages the records of these
lineages in various such texts
like the raj tarangini of kalahana etc
but historians refuse to take these
seriously and that's why we are not
taught about these and so on and so
forth right and even though we have the
names of the lineages and the kings and
all we don't know in exactly in which
which year they reigned and what was the
city we are not able to map the names of
those cities to actual geographical
locations
i mean foreign for instance you have the
kingdom of odiana
that
was there during the mahajanapadas
period but we don't know where it was
was it was it in the swath valley was it
in central india no one knows today
because we have lost all these records
so all these
records need to be looked at whatever
information is available through these
ancient records like the raj tarangini
etc and we need to try and find ways of
mapping these
records to actual time periods and so on
and so forth lots of historical research
needs to be done
and because it has not been done that's
why there is no information available at
hand
so essentially what i can say is that
india's so-called historians have
not done their job
they need to be sacked
what can i say about the razakurs of
hyderabad terrorists that's what they
were
i don't know anything
the bahara community i don't know
anything about them sorry i i haven't
studied their
history because well
i've had other things to do
okay uh can iran be used to isolate
pakistan globally as it also has access
to afghanistan
and central asia and also oil
well
actually it is iran that is being
isolated globally right now the
americans
are doing their best to isolate iran
and it's not working because the chinese
are getting involved in the
mix and they are now
entering into an alliance with iran
there is this uh
this accord or pact that the iran and
china have signed
worth uh
i don't know tens of billions of dollars
it's a 20 30 euro 30 year pact or
something like that that they've signed
recently
so it is not possible for the americans
to isolate iran because china will use
that to their advantage now
who wants to isolate pakistan globally
we want to do that but the americans
have never been really
willing to cooperate in that they have
always wanted to support pakistan or use
pakistan in some way or the other
whether it is in the afghanistan
arena or somewhere else or in the past
the americans have used pakistan against
india
and now the chinese are doing that they
are using pakistan to
keep india off balance so it's not
really possible to isolate pakistan
globally now
is iran interested in isolating pakistan
the iranians don't really have a very
good relationship with the pakistanis
it's a shia sunni issue it's a very
basic fundamental issue deep-rooted
issue so iran and pakistan can never be
really good friends
in the past the iranians have actually
sided with pakistan from time to time
against india
like in the 1971 war
the iranians offered support to pakistan
they allowed the pakistanis to
i think it was in the 1965 war or 1971 i
don't remember which one but in one of
these wars the pakistanis were able to
fly their uh
aircraft and park them in iran so that
they would not be destroyed by the
indian air force so the iranians allowed
the pakistanis to do that
and even recently the iranians allowed
pakistan to kidnap an indian businessman
kul bhushan jadhav from iranian
territory
and take him to pakistan so you know
it's it's a complicated issue the
iranians are not really our friends and
pakistan is our
sward enemy the chinese are our sworn
enemy and all of these games are going
on so it's not really possible to
isolate pakistan
as such as long as the chinese support
pakistan you can't isolate pakistan and
even the americans
are kind of
uh
using pakistan from time to time even
now they are using pakistan
for drone strikes in afghanistan and so
on i mean i heard the news a week or so
ago that there is something going on the
americans are using pakistan as a
staging
staging area for launching drone strikes
into afghanistan
so it's not really possible to isolate
pakistan the only solution is the final
solution
which is to
break pakistan up into smaller
territories
uh pashtunistan should go back to
afghanistan since should become free
balochistan should become free punjab
should become of a separate nation and
so on and the isi and the pakistan army
need to be dismantled and and dealt with
so that is the solution that india needs
to accomplish in the next five to ten
years if we want to have
long lasting peace on the western border
and once that is accomplished then we
can focus our full energies on the
bigger threat to the north
in tibet which is china
so that's what i can say about this
pawan says why do the so called woke
people do their environment awareness
campaign only during hindu festivals
because
the ultimate aim is to eradicate
hinduism wipe out hinduism and turn
india into
into a rootless nation which
actually you can see that succeeding
succeeding to some level especially
among the very young
when you have when you when you look at
the teenagers and the
early 20 year old people and all they
are quite ruthless
and they are very strongly influenced by
all this so-called vocal propaganda
so-called liberal propaganda because
it's it sounds very good it sounds very
pro environment
it sounds so pro human right so all that
and hinduism is portrayed as a very
negative very regressive backward
patriarchal
misogynistic casteist etc or religion
and therefore it is so easy to influence
the youngsters especially
into hating hinduism
and
there can then be recruited because of
the education system into all these
campaigns and activities that are
anti-hindu and that's why
so the
basic
premise of all this woke nonsense is
hindu phobia
the agenda is to destroy hinduism
and the bigger agenda is to turn india
into a rootless nation so that people
can be influenced very easily into
buying all kinds of things
so india they want to treat india as a
huge market it's all about making money
at the end
so if you can break down society break
down the social structure destroy the
family system of support
then you can influence minds very easily
because everybody is isolated and they
can be bombarded by
advertising messages and they will buy
whatever you want them to buy look at
america it's a consumer culture if
if you're feeling sad or depressed go
and do some retail therapy go buy
expensive items and it will make you
feel bad feel good for a few hours yeah
like taking a dose of drugs
so that's what they have reduced their
population too and that's what they want
to do in india as long as you have a
strong culture and civilization and
strong strong social cohesion
then it's very hard to influence you
into buying things that you don't need
so they want to destroy the indian
social structure indian culture
they want to
make everyone rootless
and they want to uh encourage the
so-called independence
of every person and individualism
because that is the
is is the key to influencing people
so make your own decisions don't don't
listen to your elders don't listen to
your family make your own decisions be
independent be strong
and then listen to our ad campaigns and
buy whatever we tell you to buy that is
the thing so the key to that is to
destroy hinduism and destroy indian
culture and that is why all these
environment
awareness campaigns are doing are done
during hindu festivals diwali is bad
bursting firecrackers is terrible for
the environment
and don't hurt animals
whereas other festivals so-called
festivals you will not talk about that
you know so that's the thing they want
to destroy hinduism so we need to resist
that and it's not just the work people
it's the
indian institutions and politicians too
who are involved in this and sports
people
i mean the job the role that a sports
person
plays in society is that of an
entertainer and that's it
so we need to stop putting these people
on these huge pedestals
a sports person is an entertainer
a borrowed person as an entertainer do
you know what vishnu gupta said about
entertainers
do you know what the arthashastra says
about entertainers
it says
tax them heavily and
relegate them to the margins of society
do not treat them
in any way
as role models
so we need to
heed our ancient wisdom
and stop putting these people on
pedestals
choose your heroes wisely
all right next question
says
please elaborate about the
israel-palestine conflict and the
position of
bharat in that jaind
while it's a old conflict
uh the region of israel was the original
homeland of the jewish people we know
that that's part of history
about 3 000 years ago or thereabouts
they had this
jewish kingdom solomon's kingdom they
had the great temple in jerusalem
jerusalem is yerushalayim it's a jewish
city
and later the you had the arabic
conquest of this region and the jews
were expelled and all that
the massacres i'm sure there were lots
of them
and it became
an arabic speaking territory
and the culture religion everything
changed and they called it philistine or
palestine
and in the 1940s israel was recreated
over there
the jewish people found their homeland
again
and that's how this by this
israel-palestine conflict
began and it's been smoldering ever
since
and india's position in that has always
been pro-palestine
ever since the time of the
congress party's regime and rule over
india india has always supported
palestine i think the
uh india established its diplomatic
relations with with israel i think quite
late in the day
there was a long time when india and
israel did not have formal
diplomatic relations
india had not recognized i think the
state of israel
and india has always had this record of
supporting palestine on international
forums
voting in favor of palestine and against
israel in the u.n and so on and so forth
it's only in the very recent times that
india has become
india has warmed its relationship with
israel today i think india has a very as
a much better
much warmer
relationship with israel and i think
it's a good thing i mean
what do we what does india what has
india ever gained
from supporting palestine it's all about
the national interest
you have to align your diplomatic
movements
and
relationships
in in the
in favor of your national interest
so what did india ever gain by
supporting palestine i do not see
anything that india ever gained by doing
that by supporting and aligning with
israel we gain a lot
we get we gain a good very strong ally a
very capable ally
we are able to uh
cooperate in this fee in the military
sphere in the technological sphere in
this in the cyber domain and so much
more
and we can share intelligence we can
align our geopolitical interests also
which are significantly in convergence
and so on and so forth
so the position that we have now taken
and we are now aligning towards that is
very much pro-israel and it is the right
direction
so i'm glad to see that
says the rig veda describes ayas or iron
this disproves the out of india theory
well congratulations sir i don't know
how it disproves it but if you think so
very good
all right let us
see what else
sham madip says there is no letter v in
bengali so i think the ancient name of
bengal was not a vanguard pradesh but
banga pradesh please correct me if i'm
wrong
see how how old is the bengali bhasha
vanga basha how long how old is it
not more than a thousand years old
before that what was speaking what was
spoken in this in this region
it was some older prakrit language which
was the parent language of of modern
bengali
so the pronunciations would have been
different before that you had pali
before that you had sanskrit
so the original language throughout
india was sanskrit
5 000 years ago there was no bengali
language
1500 years ago there was no bengali
right
so the names of places change depending
on the language depending on the
pronunciation
usually it's the pronunciations that
change
so it was vanga pradesh
for some reason the this region they
somehow the v
pronunciation disappeared it became bur
so if you want to write abhijit you
write avi jit i know that's how it is
because i've been there
so you know it's something that has
evolved over time
so the original name name was vanga
pradesh v not be
and before that i think it was called
anger
because karna was the king of anger so
that's how it goes right
the myth of saint thomas
saint thomas
so the myth of saint thomas is that this
individual came to india and he was
massacred
not massacred but he was murdered by
evil hindus on some mountain and
somewhere in southern india and that's
why there is a church there now and it
somehow proves that he came to india
look there is no evidence zero not there
is not one shred of evidence that this
person came to india
and there is no evidence that he came to
india then and that he was murdered by
indians by hindus because hindus were
inferior and he was preaching the
superior religion and that's why these
evil jealous hindus felt insecure and
that's why they had to murder him that
is the myth that has been propagated
worldwide without a single shred of
evidence
so that is the myth of saint thomas it's
a myth it's a lie it's an outline lie
outright lie it's a fabrication
hmm
sumit says did greeks take astronomy for
us from us and give astrology
from
to us
so there is this claim i have seen many
people make that we have
learned astrology or something like that
the the zodiac signs etc from the greeks
apparently we never had that and we had
to learn that from the greeks
so i have seen no evidence of that it's
just claims that people make without
evidence
uh
we over the civilization predates the
greeks by thousands of years
so if any and we know that we have
astronomical records that go back
to around 6600 bce
the uh the when the greeks
came to the court of the mauryans or
came to the court of the chandra of
chandragupta maurya our emperor they
discovered that we indians had a
calendar the
saptarshi calendar
that dated back to some which which
reckoned time from 6 600 something bce
onwards
so that's how old our reckoning of time
was and if you have a calendar you have
astronomical observations and so on
because that's how calendars are made
that's how you start
keeping track of
time and we also have evidence of
astronomical observations from northern
india which dates back to about 5000 bc
or 3000 bc or something like that the
the oldest known record of a supernova
so we had and that also has two
so-called
it has the consolation of orion and some
other something else over there so it's
clear
that we already understood
astronomy we already had the concept of
constellations
and the zodiac signs
way before greek civilization was ever
born
so this is a myth in short
caitanya says why was india communist
for so long
uh when was india communist
did we have a communist constitution do
we have communist laws did we have a
communist government
i am not sure what you mean sir but uh
india hasn't been communist
india has been socialist
socialism is a different thing it's not
exactly communism
you could you could interpret socialism
as soft marxism or soft communism
communism means everybody lives in a
commune there is no private property
everything is collectivized that is
communism so india has never been
communist
avishkar says why is the saraswati river
not been found
go to google maps
go to google earth you will see it you
will see the dry riverbed of the
saraswati starting from the himalayas
and going all the way down to the to the
indian ocean it has been found everyone
knows where it is
so
if you want to know more details check
out my earlier videos and you will find
more information there
what is my view on marriage
get married it's a good thing
um
okay let me let me revisit this what's
my view on marriage
see nowadays there is this uh
there is this new uh
view that is being aired that you don't
need to get married married have a few
live-in relationships keep changing your
partner every two or three years like
it's fast food right
like you change your ideology every few
years
and so on and so forth this is
a means of destabilizing society it's a
means of of uprooting of making people
rootless
because we have a certain
culture
that uh considers marriage to be
sacred
not until you get divorced but it's a
it's a lifelong thing right
and this is now inter it is now been
reinterpreted as a patriarchal custom
and therefore the the voc propaganda or
the leftist marxist propaganda
propaganda is that marriage is a
patriarchal institution it is something
that enslaves women
it is something that turns women into
the possession of men
and therefore we need to
do away with this institution of
marriage
right
have multiple partners
and so on and so forth so it is
it is a tool that is being used to
to make people rootless especially the
youngsters i'll never get married i
don't want to have kids and so on
so i think it is it is very dangerous
for society marriage is a good thing
and don't fall for this leftist
marxist
etc propaganda
okay don't get sick johan says you have
said instead of partition we should have
done a civil war i have never said we
should have done a civil war okay
but what's happened in sri lanka between
sinai's and tamils which ruined the
entire nation wouldn't india have
suffered that
okay
so
what i have said is that
i have not advocated civil war
of what i had observed is that jinnah
threatened
that he would unleash a civil war if
partition was not done and he was not
given pakistan
so i said that let's compare this with
what happened in america in the united
states
in the 1860s the civil war
that's when the south
of the nation had seceded
there was an attempt to partition the
nation and abraham lincoln preferred
going to war then allowing the country
to break up
so i said that hypothetically
that was a better solution so if jinnah
had gone ahead with his threat of
carrying out a civil war i said that
maybe there was a good solution because
after independence after the partition
we are still at war with pakistan which
is the continuation of the civil war
and today it's a nuclear-armed civil war
isn't it
so that's what i had said
so maybe it would have been a good idea
that if jinnah had unleashed the civil
war we should have fought back and
defeated those who tried to break our
nation and dealt with that problem once
and for all
that would have been a better solution
than having this prolonged conflict
which still festers today and which
could someday become a nuclear war
now when you speak about sri lanka the
civil war that happened between the
sinai and the tamils
the sinhalese were oppressing the tamils
they had relegated the thomas to the
status of second-class citizens
that's what happened and that's why
there was a civil war and there was a
lot of interference from the west
so that is a totally different scenario
there is a completely different scenario
it has no relevance
in the in the context of the partition
scenario
and when it comes to the ltte
the ltte was not a hindu verse this
civil war was not a hindu versus
buddhist
conflict
did you do you even know that
prabhakaran was a converted christian
he was being manipulated by the west
all the funds all the arms were coming
in from the west
from countries like norway etc
this was an attempt to christianize sri
lanka
i am not saying that what the the
atrocities that were done on the tamils
or on the sinali's anything was good no
war is a bad thing
but this is what the west has been doing
in sri lanka
in other parts of the world for decades
for centuries the civil war in rwanda
was perpetrated by the west
it was the west the catholic church was
the puppet master they
created the conditions that led to this
genocide
and the same thing was being done in sri
lanka by the norwegians or whoever it
was
so prabhakaran was a converted christian
and the ltt was essentially a tool of
the west to
to destabilize
and christianize sri lanka
so that's what it was it was a totally
different scenario what happened in sri
lanka between the sinai's and the tamils
was being controlled by the west they
wanted to keep this region
under turmoil
in order to increase their influence
and
and re-engineer the
demographics of sri lanka
so it has nothing to do with the indian
scenario nothing at all it's a totally
different scenario totally different
context
if there was a civil war in india it
would have been started
by
jinnah and by the pro partition
supporters
right
that has no no relevance i mean that has
no parallels with what happened in sri
lanka
okay so that's the answer to that sir
sampradhi asks what's my opinion on
banning firecrackers during diwali
that is
just
so that is a symptom of hindu phobia the
indian state the indian nation is a
hindu phobic apartheid state
only hindu customs are being banned
under the guise of environmental
protection
or reducing pollution or whatever this
is nothing but hindu phobia
nothing else the same firecrackers are
allowed during other festivals of other
religions
isn't that apartheid isn't that double
standards isn't that delegating hindus
to the status of second-class citizens
firecrackers are not banned anywhere
else in the world for any other festival
but only in india only during diwali we
have to resist this
so now this time in diwali we saw that
bursting firecrackers has been turned
into an act of civil disobedience
isn't that interesting the simple act of
bursting a firecracker is now an act of
civil disobedience and this year it was
observed that diwali was
celebrated with a great deal of vigor
and gusto
and even people who had not burst
firecrackers for firecrackers for a
couple of decades made it a point to go
out and burst firecrackers
so this is the reaction we are seeing to
this endophobia that is now becoming
more and more mainstreamed
in india
so i think it is an act of hindu phobia
if
the courts or the government were to ban
bursting firecrackers it's nothing but
hindu phobia you know what's happening
the fireworks industry is in shivakasi
in tamil nadu
but the people who do that who
are involved in this industry are all
hindus
if you ban firecrackers their industry
will get destroyed they will become
destitute and then there will be easy
targets for conversion to certain other
religions
that is the long-term plan
that's why we need to resist this
and we need to support this industry one
night of bursting firecrackers does
nothing to the
environment right
so that's what i have to say about this
richard says don't you think indian
states should be reorganized the states
are nonetheless the same since the
british times
like like there could be a state called
braj bundelkhand bhagal khan and up
i think it's an interesting suggestion
uh we have states that have been drawn
the boundaries have been drawn on on the
basis of linguistics it's these are
linguistic states
now when you draw straight boundaries
based on linguists on language and
culture we are creating the sense of
otherness
and certain states are quite small
mizoram manipur
etc
and certain states are enormous up
it's bigger than most countries in the
world
it is such a lopsided situation
what i would say is that
i'm just saying let's think about this
why not reorganize india into a number
of small states
maybe you could have five tamil states
in in 12
hindi speaking states
etc it you know the smaller the unit of
governance is the more efficient the
governance is
so if you have one chief minister
for an enormous state like maharashtra
or u.p
it is very hard for the chief minister
to take care of every single person in
the state
that chief minister is unreachable
when one chief minister
is is the head of state for 300 million
people
but if you have one chief minister for
10 million people it's way way easier
for somebody to reach that person and
it's way easier for the chief minister
to effectively administer that small
region
so it is certainly something that we
should think about
reorganize the internal
divisions
the administrative
divisions of india
and make it more equal and more logical
you know i'm not saying that we should
break up states and and divide people
and all that
it's just one country so there's no
question of that but
or reimagine and reconfigure the
administrative dividend divisions that
would uh certainly give better
governance and better
um
better access to government officials to
the common people so something like that
certainly is something we should think
about in the long term next 10 20 years
i'm sure it would be of significant
benefit
to the common people of india
okay let's take some more questions
what do you want to say to those people
who question women's clothes in the name
of sanatan dharma
i mean who's questioning what
i'm not very sure about who is
questioning
what about women's clothes in sanatana
dharma there is no compulsion
or restriction of any kind on the kind
of clothes
men or women can wear you can wear
whatever you choose
there is nothing in any book that says
you can't wear this or you can't wear
that
and if some people question something
like that i'm sure they're in a big
minority india is a very liberal country
i mean the real
definition of liberalism we are a very
liberal culture we have we have always
accepted all everything
all kinds of diversity all lifestyles so
i don't think
there is any big issue like that if some
people questions question
certain
lifestyle choices they should simply be
ignored
dheeraj says climate change is getting
worse day by day
why are world leaders not taking strong
action against climate change
you see the thing is this
yeah i'm not denying climate change
climate change is a real thing it is
certainly there and a significant
portion of that significant component of
climate change is mediated by human
activity
and this began during the so-called
industrial revolution
when the western countries started
polluting the world
in a completely irresponsible fashion
and they stole the wealth of
asia and africa they enrich themselves
and now today asia and africa are trying
to catch up
and bring themselves back to that level
and
they will do whatever is required to do
that
which includes burning coal the western
nations burned cold for two three
centuries and now they want india and
china to stop burning coal it doesn't
work like that
you can't force people
to not
um
develop their nations so this is the
conundrum we are facing the real problem
in climate change is animal agriculture
more than 50 percent of all pollution
all deforestation is because of is
caused by animal agriculture the beef
industry
it is the beef industry that is the
major driver of climate change and that
is all driven by the west
and they refuse
to even address this question they
refuse to even recognize the fact that
the beef industry is the primary driver
of climate change globally
they want to throw all the blame on
india and china and
they treat india and china on equal
footing when when when blaming them when
china is a far worse polluter than india
so you see the problem is that climate
change is real it is certainly being
driven by human activity
but every nation
in the current
geopolitical scenario
in the westphalian world that we live in
the westfalian system
every nation
competes with every other nation
and every nation can only do what is
best for them because if you try and do
something that's best for the world
you're gonna be left far behind by
everybody else
and that's why nothing's gonna work
world leaders get together once in a
while they set targets 20 30 50 years
down the line
but they have to do what is best for
their country so because we are all
divided into these
mutually exclusive and highly
competitive nations because we treat
geopolitics is a zero-sum game
and we want to do what is best for our
country today
and because we are unable to reach a
consensus that's why nothing is being
happen is being done
and there is no progress on climate
change there is so much plastic being
dumped into the oceans
the west is refusing to cut down on the
beef industry and so on and so forth and
they want to keep on blaming
india and china
so
that's why nothing is happening
sad
and the problem is that it's going to
adversely affect the future generations
those who are not yet born they're going
to inherit a world that is so much worse
than what it is today
such a huge population eight nine ten
billion
on the planet also all this
deforestation all the oceans are choked
with plastic
and so on and so forth it's going to be
bad in the future unless we get our act
together but it will not happen
unless something changes drastically
which i don't see it happening anytime
soon
how are you we are all very well sir
thank you for asking
one of the dongra says why did russia
sell a last cut of the u.s i think i had
taken this up in detail in a previous
episode but they sold a last cut of the
us because they were very much
preoccupied with events that were
happening in
eurasia
and because they did not see any benefit
that would that would accrue from
holding on to alaska
at that time alaska was a big piece of
wilderness it was so far away from
moscow
even
i mean it was not even sure whether they
could have been able to hold on to it
or be able to administer it effectively
and at that time all the natural
resources over there all the mineral
resources all the oil had not yet be not
yet been discovered
and that's why they regarded it as an
unimport as a relatively
unimportant piece of territory and
what we have also realized is that there
were these conflicts going on the great
game
between
the russian empire and the british
empire going on for the control of
central asia the russians had lost the
crimean war
in the middle of the 19th century so
they had more pressing issues
closer to home and alaska seemed like
something that was really far away and
it was not really important
so they decided to
uh
sell it to the u.s
and take some cash
and and acquire some cash in return
so it was a very short-sighted
short-term move
and the americans gained a lot from that
does the multiverse exist the multiverse
is pseudoscience there is no evidence
for it it's not even science it's
it's more like philosophy i mean there
is no scientific basis to it
because it cannot be proven
and it cannot be falsified and therefore
there is no evidence
that it exists and we will most likely
never be able to prove or disprove
the existence of universes beyond our
own
this is a good question
raut says should india leave the
commonwealth
well the commonwealth is a collection of
nations that were all once ruled by
britain
so it's a collection of former colonies
of the uk
and what do we have in common
that we are all mentally colonized
the question is really this that what do
we benefit from being part of the
commonwealth
and if the criterion of for being a
member of the commonwealth is that you
were once ruled by the british
then even the u.s should be a member of
the commonwealth
because the u.s was ruled by the british
in the past
before the
american war of independence
but the americans fought for their
independence
they defeated the british kicked them
out
and created their own country
and they have chosen not to be a part of
the commonwealth maybe out of
self-respect
and what that tells you is that india
lacks a certain degree of self-respect
and that's why we are still a member of
the commonwealth
i mean the simple question is what do we
gain from being a member of this
of this grouping of nations is there any
actual tangible tangible benefit for
india if there is any we should stay
within it otherwise we should leave i
mean there's no real need to be part of
a group of losers of a club of losers
right
so i think it is best that we leave the
commonwealth but i don't see that
happening anytime soon because
we are so
set in our ways and we want to just
continue the so-called traditions
as if they are somehow good for us
says should post modernism and
intersectionality be read by every
thinking indian
to understand how the west plays with
our history you know i have
in the past tried to understand what
post-modernism is
i have tried i have tried hard i have
never been able to figure out whether
there is any logic behind it
it's just word salad that's it
there is no real theory of
post-modernism
jacques de rida and foucault and all
this so bishop foucault and all these
so-called
french intellectuals who created this
theory of post-modernism
i have tried to understand what it is i
have simply not succeeded
because i understand things when there
is some logic behind it
and similarly with intersectionality
everything is intersectional come on
so you know what i think it is best that
all intelligent indians stay away from
this
the best way to
deal with these attempts to recolonize
us or to mentally colonize us is to
is to study our own history our own
philosophy our own literature
and become cognizant of who we really
are that is the best way
to combat
what the west is doing and the west see
post-modernism intersectionality and
critical race theory whatever it is
these are newer manifestations
of marxism that's what it is
you can call them neo-marxism so if you
want to really understand how societies
are divided how these uh
how this social engineering is carried
out just try and figure out what marxism
is
marxism always takes new shapes and new
forms and the latest
shapes and forms are all of these you
know
post-modernism intersectionality
critical race theory which is nowadays
they are trying to apply it to india as
well
to create newer and newer
and more and more fault lines and
divisions within society
so as long as you can understand the
basic thesis of marxism and how it
divides society into classes
and then
play one class against the other then
you will understand how it works
uchiha says a claim that there was a
pre-islamic vedic culture in arabia well
show me the evidence and i will agree
if there is evidence i will agree to it
if there is a lack of evidence i'll say
we need to find evidence or maybe there
is none
so i have personally
not seen anything that is definitive
proof
of vedic culture
in arabia there are certain things that
are similar
to indian culture
similar but not the same
they did have goddesses they did have
polytheism
they did worship
stone they did consider stone idols to
be sacred
they did have things that
kind of resemble
shivlings
etc etc etc
but many polytheistic societies
have these cultural manifestations
so is it certainly definitely
definitively vedic culture
we can't say for sure
right it was certainly a polytheistic
culture
but there is no
uh
conclusive
evidence
that this was vedic culture
so i would say that the the
claim is still not proven
okay avishkar
says why is the saraswati river not
being searched that's because we found
it
we know where it is
it's dried out but we know where the
riverbed is
i think the same question is being asked
repeatedly
my answer is i don't know anything about
them because i have never bothered to
study about them it's never interested
me
my interests are in certain things
everything in the world doesn't interest
me and therefore i will tell you
honestly and transparently i don't know
much about this community
okay let's take some other questions
hopefully something that has not been
answered before
let me try to find some interesting
questions
why are we not making web series on our
hindu puranas in mythological stories
just like the game of thrones
we have more interesting stories to
share the share to the world
by this we can reach out to the masses
you know what bollywood has all the
money in the world but they refuse to do
that
like you said i agree with you 100
our stories our ancient stories are more
interesting than any marvel universe
movie they can make
it is way more interesting than the game
of thrones
the mahabharata ramayana if you could
turn them into
a series with like say a few
seasons with the kind of investment they
had in the game of thrones then just
imagine how incredibly interesting and
and what a spectacular it would be
and why will they not do it because it
will then tell indians how great their
past was how great their culture was
and they don't want indians to know this
and that's why they will not take up
a project such as this
because it will
show to the world how great indian
civilization once was
so that's why it's not being done so
what i would say is that you know there
are lots of rich people in in this
country lots of businessmen who don't
know where to throw their money
why can't they take this up
i don't understand why why why they
refuse to take this up today we have the
technology we don't need to use
bollywood's
people
to create a series such as this
but somehow there is a lack of vision
there is a lack of leadership there is a
lack of imagination and that's why it's
not happening but yes this is i would
call it low hanging fruit
it's right there for the taking
if somebody wants to invest in such a
series
okay i'm getting the same i'm seeing the
same questions repeated all the time
ashutosh says does italy have some
secret library to be accessed only by
the pope and his subordinates
and does it have all of our stolen
knowledge real sanskrit texts
there certainly is
a secret library in the vatican that is
closed off to all to all outsiders
only the inner circle in the vatican
has access to it we don't know what is
there in there
so yes there could be some ancient
indian knowledge hidden over there that
is certainly possible certainly possible
the existence of this library is known
but it is
not open to the public
right let's take some more questions
kunal says why the shudras were subdued
by the brahmanas it is a lie
it is a neo-colonial lie it is a lie
that has been created by the british
by their missionaries
in order
to create divisions in india's society
we it is true that uh
in the post-invasion history of india
there were all these divisions on
society because indian society was not
able to function the way it was it had
evolved as it was designed to be
there were all kinds of restrictions
placed upon society by the invaders by
the occupiers by the turks and later by
the
by the europeans
and it was
in their
interest
to play one section of india's society
against another section of indian
society make some people
richer make some people very poor and
then blame the oppressed oppression and
all that on
indians not on the british for instance
for instance
many famines were were engineered by the
british in india
and if you watch
certain movies
there are certain movies by people like
satyajit ray
horrible depressing movies
they are considered to be masterpieces
of indian cinema
uh so there is i remember when i was a
kid i watched some movie by satyajid it
was a black and white movie it dealt
with the famine in bengal which the
british had engineered
and the way they portrayed it was they
were satay was trying to blame
the famine
on marwaris who had hoarded apparently
all the grain
so the famine that the british
engineered in this movie it was blamed
on the marwaris who and it was alleged
that they were hoarding grain and food
stocks and that's why the people of
bengal were starving
that's the kind of portrayal that was
done
by satyajit ray
so this is what's been a recurring theme
in the in colonial in post-colonial in
colonial and post-colonial india
whether it was during the turkic times
or during the european occupation of
india
that all everything that went wrong in
india was blamed on certain sections of
indian society and when you want to
destroy hinduism
and replace it with a foreign religion
blame those who have been tasked with
preserving indian culture
so in indian society those who were
learned were called brahmans
and they were the ones who would
carry forward
indian culture because they were in
charge of preserving it so blame them so
that they can be marginalized so that
indian culture in all the memories
disappear
so that's what has that that's that's
been the colonial project in india
especially after the british came to
power and they occupied india and today
it is taught in our textbooks and all
that and we all believe yeah yeah the
sudras were
subdued by the brahmanas the brahmins
are the great oppressors hinduism is now
called brahminism apparently
this new terminology is now mainstreamed
in india's textbooks in india's
universities by india's historians who
have nothing else to do but to create
new divisions in society they will not
research india's real history
there is so much of india's history
which has never been touched by
historians they don't want to research
it but they want to find new ways of
creating of of blaming indians
for the oppression that was perpetrated
by foreigners
so please do not believe this nonsense
brahmins did not oppress anybody they
did not subdue anybody
these four divisions of society were
created by the british
india was a land of jaati and varna
which is a very complex system
[Music]
we never had this four category division
which the british created
all right let me move on from this
okay i want to know
which nations that exists today like
pakistan nepal etc were
a part of akanda bharat when you speak
about akanda bharat you're talking about
uh the indian subcontinent which is the
homeland of india's civilization
so pakistan was part of it afghanistan
was part of it afghanistan was called
gandhar in ancient times
or nepal was always part of it it was
part of india
nepal became a separate kingdom during
the
during the 1700s
prithvi narayan shah was the king who
created a separate kingdom there
in the
newar valley
it was later it was later called nepal
and again bangladesh is just bengal it's
vanga pradesh
and similarly sri lanka lanka was also i
mean the people are the same ethnicity
as us as indians
the senate and tamil languages are both
indian languages
right sinali is is classified as an
indo-european language indo-aryan
language and so on
so all of this was part of what you what
you could call akanda bharath
and indian civilization extended much
further east
burma thailand vietnam cambodia laos
indonesia malaysia singapore
and the philippines all of this was part
of india's
greater civilization
okay let's take some
more
comments
my opinion on sun tzu interesting book
uh the art of war you can certainly uh
learn a lot from the from that uh
book
very interesting stratagems
especially on how to
make yourself
invulnerable to attack
and then you can once you do that then
you can start go on the offensive and
that sort of thing so it's a very
interesting book
uh it is not 100 sure if sun tzu is a
historical character
maybe it's a collection of ancient
wisdom from china's
ancient history
as we know china is about two and a half
or three thousand years old
so maybe it's a collection of ancient
chinese wisdom and they have attributed
it to a fictional person called zhu or
maybe he is somebody who actually
existed we are not sure
about that
but if this individual actually existed
and he had so much experience in warfare
then all the warfare that he did was
against his own fellow chinese that's
also an interesting thing that comes out
of this
so yes it is
what i know is the book that is supposed
to have been authored by this person
it's a very interesting book i think and
it's a very small flimsy book anybody
could read that in a few hours but to
actually understand and internalize the
concepts will take longer it's certainly
something that everybody should read
and try to learn from
okay let's take some more interesting
questions
deepan bhattacharya says what are my
thoughts on swami vivekananda saying
that beef eating was not a sin
you know what i don't really know what
uh swami vivekananda said or did not say
i have not studied his life or his
writings or his history
honestly speaking i don't know much
about about swami vivekananda lots of
people say he was a very great person
i'm sure he was but i am not an
authority
on swami vivekananda
my uh
i have been fascinated with india's
ancient history and the big picture
history of the world which is why i am
so which is why i am able to understand
geopolitics and the global
context that we are living in
i have not been interested in very
small uh
eras or episodes of indian history and
one of the things that i have not
studied in depth is
the life of swami vivekananda that's why
i can't really comment about this with
any real authority
meera says do god and the concept of
reincarnation really exist i don't know
i don't know some people claim there is
reincarnation and some people claim that
some kids uh
exhibit memories from a previous
lifetime
well i haven't seen any that person
personally
so from personal experience i say i
don't know
and it is something that is beyond the
uh
beyond the ambit of scientific inquiry
this is something that falls in the
realm of spirituality it goes beyond
science
so my simple question is i do not know
i don't know
lipton barua says does mongolia lie in
central asia or eastern asia it lies in
eastern asia central asia is
north and west of india kazakhstan
tajikistan kyrgyzstan uzbekistan
all of that is central asia
mongolia is east of that
so one could call it eastern asia
okay let's take some more questions
current says you've mentioned about
balkanization of pakistan but do you
think it can happen really
considering the fact that pakistan has
nukes
is that the reason we haven't taken back
pok yet
you know any country can can break up
whether they have nukes or not it all
depends on their internal cohesion
and the kind of governance they have and
whether the people support the
government
pakistan has a lot of internal fault
lines
the pashtuns
they owe their allegiance to pashtun
islam to the people
to afghanistan actually
the sindhis the real hindis are not at
all happy with the
punjabi yoke that they are under the
balochi people
they are struck there they are groaning
under decades of oppression by the
pakistani army
and so on and so forth so there are so
many internal fault lights within
pakistan
the people of kashmir
[Music]
they are being marginalized in their own
land
punjabis and pashtuns are being settled
there
so do you think they are happy about it
no they would rather prefer to go back
and reintegrate with india
so it is certainly possible to balkan as
pakistan
provided you engineer engineer it
properly over a certain period of time
whether they have nukes or not is
immaterial
the ussr had nukes
the ussr was balkanized well there you
go
why haven't we taken back people yet
because we still have because in the
past we never had the political will to
do that
we went to war with pakistan multiple
times every war was initiated by the
pakistanis we could have taken back pok
in 65 in 71
and even in 1948
but we never had the political will to
do that
the nuclear problem came in much later
so i think it's a question of political
will nothing else i think it can happen
in the next five to ten years we should
not wait longer than that
all right
let's take some other questions
mother india says please answer how can
i be a successful person
in your life in my life
please understand that you are an
intelligent person you are somebody with
everybody is born with intelligence with
curiosity
with good qualities with some real value
so how to become successful in life is
invest in yourself
give yourself the best chance of
succeeding
right uh do
try and maximize your potential when you
are young learn everything you can learn
things that are beyond the syllabus that
is taught in school
learn some actual skills
so
try to learn something beyond acquiring
degrees learn some actual skills like
coding or something like that you know
some real world skills and in your
early adult life in your 20s maybe early
30s try and get as much experience as
possible in different jobs in different
industries and so on and by the time
you're in your 30s mid-30s you'll start
under making sen
you'll start being able to understand
what the world is really like
so try and acquire as much experience
and wisdom as you can by that time
and that's when you can start
giving something back to society
so that is a very in in very brief in in
a very general sense
a kind of roadmap to how to be
successful in life
so understand that you have a great deal
of value you have a great deal of talent
and quality is good qualities and
give yourself the best chance of
succeeding by doing these things
aditya singh says do you have any theory
on the dyatlov pass incident
in russia
in which about nine hikers died
yeah that's an interesting story i had
read about long ago i think it happened
in the 1960s
was it a long time ago
so these hikers went into this this
region in siberia some
some pass and they were camping there in
the snow it was very cold
very far away from any major urban
urban
settlement
and then they disappeared they did not
come back when they were supposed to
come back then a search party was sent
to find them
and they were found all dead all dead
all frozen
and it looked like something very
strange had happened
they were wearing very less clothing
even though it was freezing outside
and some of them had broken bones
and things like that so they have never
been able to really explain
the mystery of how this happened how why
did these people die why did they run
out of their tents and go and freeze in
in the open
and so on and so forth
so i don't have any theory it's a very
strange mystery some people say that
there was some supernatural element
involved in this
some people have theorized that there
was some aliens alien abduction or
something that happened
some ufo was there or whatever i don't
know it's a very interesting mystery
and it looks like it has still not been
been satisfactorily explained
so interesting
is there any intelligent civilization
before human existence
it's possible
see because if you look at the uh
geology of the earth
because of tectonic activity
uh
whatever is part of the surface of the
earth it all gets subsumed and it all
goes underground
within
a few hundred million years
within half
about half a billion years or so
everything that was that is overground
gets
subsumed under the surface of the earth
and
new material from under the earth comes
out and becomes the surface
so if there was a big civilization a
successful intelligent civilization
let's say a billion years before today
all the traces of that would have
completely vanished by now
and therefore it is certainly possible
that there may have been
a significantly intelligent and
successful civilization a billion or
maybe even two billion years before
today
that we don't know about
and maybe we'll never know about it is
certainly possible uh
i'm not sure what they call this theory
but there was some interesting name that
people had given to this
so yeah yeah it's certainly possible
and then it's an interesting thing to
think about that we know so little
about our planet and its past
okay do we have any other interesting
questions
let's see
webov says hello from japan arigato
arigato hello nice to have you here
thanks for thanks for being here
uh let's see some more questions
okay this is a question that i get often
what was the actual amount of wealth
that the british drained from india
so economists have tried to calculate
this and the
figure that they have come up with is
around
45 trillion dollars
in today's money so that is an
incredible amount of wealth that was
stolen from india
and uh
it has been corroborated by multiple
economists based on the calculations
that they've done and on based on the
data that we have about what the british
stole from india
i mean i recently saw some news about uh
a shipwreck was found in the
english channel which is which is
between
britain
and france
a shipwreck was found it was a ship that
was sailing from india
to england
and i think it sank somewhere there
and it had several
thousand tons
of
silver which was being taken out of
india
and being transported
to england so just imagine there was
just one one ship out of hundreds
that extracted wealth out of india so
the amount of wealth these people have
stolen from india is incredible
so the typical figure that people uh
give us economists have calculated is
about
45 trillion which is
about four or five times
the current gdp
of the uk
which is incredible so even if they were
to pay it back they would have to go
bankrupt for a few years to pay it back
which they will never do
so that tells you how
rich india and how prosperous india was
in the past
chuching says how can one become an
astronaut
i think astronauts are typically chosen
from fighter pilots
uh there is an astronaut training
program which is going on right now
because india is in this decade planning
to launch uh
astronauts into space
indian astronauts on an indian rocket
so i think a number of uh astronauts are
undergoing training right now and these
are all
fighter pilots
so it it has been found that the
people who are successful as fighter
pilots have all the physical and mental
uh traits
that are suitable for being an astronaut
so that is one way to become an
astronaut you become a fighter pilot but
today if you look in the u.s almost
anybody can become an astronaut as long
as you are reasonably physically fit
so
i think recently uh um
what's his name the the the actor who
played
uh
captain kirk
in the star trek series he went into
space he's more than 90 years old
so even a 90 plus year old guy can go
into space and come back that happened
just a couple of weeks ago so today i
think anybody
can become an astronaut as long as
you're physically fit and you have the
certain mental traits
of you maybe you must you should be able
to uh stay confined in a enclosed space
for a few hours and that sort of thing
as long as as long as you can take that
and as long as you're physically fit you
can certainly become an astronaut but if
you want to join the indian space
program which is in its infancy
then you need to be a fighter pilot as
of today maybe 10 20 years down the line
maybe anybody will be able to go into
space maybe we will even have space
tourism in which civilians can go into
space for a few minutes
as tourists
so today you if you are an indian if you
want to become part of the indian space
program the manned space flight program
then you need to be a fighter pilot a
test pilot or something like that in the
future anybody will be able to do that
so that's what i can say
okay let's take some more questions
sonali i think i have a couple of videos
about sonali you can check it out
uh
yeah this is a question by manthan about
the sonali
excavations
i have a couple of videos about that
so please check that out i will take
something else right
now okay
let's take some interesting questions i
i am seeing a lot of repeated questions
this is a question by ismail
what led to the islamization of turks
did it also lead to the downfall of the
abbasid empire through militarization
this is a very interesting question
so let's let's go back in history and
what is the origin of the turks of the
turkic peoples
uh
the origin of the turks is essentially
the same as the origin of the mongol
people they
if you go back about two two and a half
thousand years before today
you will find that the
turks and the mongols were the same
people their ancestors were the same
people they were called the hunnic
peoples the chinese called them the new
people show new people
and
their word for human being was
even today in the mongolian language the
word for human is hunu
so
that is the origin of the turkic people
they were a polytheistic culture
they
worshipped the god the main the main god
was thangri
and the the female counterpart was umai
i think
and they had a number of other
divinities as well they also had
ancestor worship and animism in that so
that was the original culture of the
turkic people
now the turks were nomads they
they lived all across and traveled all
across across central asia eurasia all
that
and there were multiple turkic or hunik
invasions of india in the first century
a.d
uh the shweta hunas the white horns the
hephthalites those were hunnic or turkic
invaders and some of them were able to
successfully conquer certain parts of
northern india
present in northern india present
afghanistan
etc
and
they practiced hinduism and buddhism
so they practiced whatever culture they
came in contact with you know that is
the trait of polytheistic people and
later on
after the advent of islam after the
the first and second caliphate uh
became prominent that's when the central
asian turks
came in in contact with the arabs and
with islam and eventually some of them
were islamized
or the
mechanics and dynamics of how this
happened is kind of lost in time but it
is in the
later half of the first millennium ad
that the turkic peoples
came in contact
with islam and slowly many of them
started adopting islam
there was a time when
certain turkic rulers
in northern india in afghanistan
actually
fought against
the
islamic invaders
so it's a very interesting scenario i
mean history is very strange and very
interesting
turks actually defended india
from islamic invaders at some point in
time
but later the the the main
uh the majority of turks
came in contact with islam they became
islamized
and if you look at the history of turkey
the the
the first
turkic
ruler
who came into anatolia was i believe
suleiman shah
and it is not quite sure whether he had
converted to islam by the time or not or
whether he was still practicing uh the
ancestral culture of the turks
so what i mean to say is that and even
this individual called erthugrul
so now nowadays there is this very
famous very very
successful
tv series
a turkish tv series which portrays
urthagrul as um as a muslim
but actually it's it's
disputed whether he had converted to
islam or whether he even existed for
sure so all of this is right is is kind
of lost in time you know the origins of
the islamization of the turkic people
are quite hazy they have not been
properly documented but it happened
sometime maybe in the late
second half of the first millennium 80
or the beginnings
of the second millennium ed
eventually the turks became islamized
and they
were able to
conquer the eastern roman empire the
byzantine roman empire and they
established the ottoman empire and the
last
caliphate the ottoman caliphate there
so yeah that's what i can say about this
but it's a very interesting question
as minor says can't we develop a program
or an algorithm to decrypt sanskrit and
its branches etc
whatever branches there are and try to
trace it backwards to translate the
manuscripts like google certainly we can
certainly use machine translation
machine learning
and all that to try and
make better sense of the linguistics of
india
the very incredibly rich linguistics of
india we have so many older languages
the prakrit languages
we have
uh languages that have gone extinct we
have so many dialects that are still
spoken today
we don't quite know what is the
relationship
between the languages
of various parts of india with each
other
and so on so it is certainly worthwhile
to do that
and that's the kind of
research that historians and scientists
need to be doing
instead of trying to find divisions in
society or engineer divisions in society
so yes it certainly is possible it would
need some funding but you could create
some such program in the iit's or
something you know
that would be very interesting
so yes this is something that i have
said i have spoken about in the past we
could even use
such algorithms to try and decrypt the
script of the indus and saraswati valley
region
so yeah i hope it happens i hope the
somebody takes it up
right okay do we have anything else
coming in
lots of questions lots of questions
shivan says why in india is
thorium plant not still ready
think india had
one of the most advanced thorium reactor
programs in the world
i think in the late 90s early 2000s
after that i don't know what happened
it's certainly something that india
should take up because the thorium
reactors are also very feasible they
would certainly
it certainly works and india has one of
the biggest reserves of thorium
in the world
so it would
kind of free india from the need to
import uranium from other countries if
you can
build reactors that use thorium as fuel
so i don't know what is the current
status right now of the thorium reactor
program but it's something that we
should certainly pursue
with a great deal of seriousness
all right
okay i think that should be it for today
it's been nearly two hours so i'm going
to stop it here
all right thank you so much for all your
questions it was great fun answering
them and let's keep doing this so next
week i will have one session that will
be based on the comments
i will take questions from comments and
the other session will be a live chat
session like today
so that's what we will do next week so
for tonight thank you very much for
all your questions thank you for
watching and i will see you very soon
in next week's episode thank you very
much
and good day goodbye bye